Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Swam upon the open ocean,
uipi aavoja syviä;
Drifting like a fallen pine-tree,
kulki kuusisna hakona,
Like a rotten branch of fir-tree,
petäjäisnä pehkiönä
During six days of the summer,
kuusi päiveä kesäistä,
And for six nights in succession,
kuusi yötä järkiähän,
While the sea spread wide before him,
eessänsä vesi vetelä,
And the sky was clear above him.
takanansa taivas selvä.
Thus he swam for two nights longer,
Uip' on vielä yötä kaksi,
And for two days long and dreary.
kaksi päiveä pisintä.
When the ninth night darkened round him,
Niin yönä yheksäntenä,
And the eighth day had passed over,
kaheksannen päivän päästä
Sudden anguish came upon him,
toki tuskaksi tulevi,
And his pain grew ever greater.
painuvi pakolliseksi.
From his toes his nails were dropping,
Kun ei ole kynttä varpahissa
And the joints from off his fingers.
eikä sormissa niveltä.
Then the aged Väinämöinen
Siinä vanha Väinämöinen
Spoke in words like those which follow:
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Woe to me, unhappy creature,
"Voi minä poloinen poika,
Overburdened with misfortune!
voi poika polon-alainen,
I have wandered from my country,
kun läksin omilta mailta,
And my ancient home abandoned.
elomailta entisiltä
'Neath the open sky for ever,
iäkseni ilman alle,
Driven along in sun and moonlight,
kuuksi päiväksi kululle,
Rocked about by winds for ever,
tuulten tuuiteltavaksi,
Tossed about by every billow,
aaltojen ajeltavaksi
On the wide expanse of water,
näillä väljillä vesillä,
Out upon the open ocean,
ulapoilla auke'illa!
Here I live a cold existence,
Vilu on täällä ollakseni,
And 'tis painful thus to wallow,
vaiva värjätelläkseni,
Always tossing on the billows,
aina aalloissa asua,
On the surface of the waters.
veen selällä seurustella.
"Now, alas, I know no longer
"Enkä tuota tieäkänä,
How to lead this life of sadness
miten olla, kuin eleä
In this everlasting trouble,
tällä inhalla iällä,
In an age when all is fleeting.
katovalla kannikalla:
Shall I rear in wind a dwelling,
tuulehenko teen tupani,
Build a house upon the waters?
vetehenkö pirtin veistän?
"If I rear in wind a dwelling,
"Teen mä tuulehen tupani:
Then the wind would not sustain it;
ei ole tuulessa tukea;
If I build a house on water,
veistän pirttini vetehen:
Then the waves will drift it from me."
vesi viepi veistokseni."
Came a bird from Lapland flying,
Lenti lintunen Lapista,
From the north-east came an eagle,
kokkolintu koillisesta.
Not the largest of the eagles,
Ei ole kokko suuren suuri
Nor was he among the smallest,
eikä kokko pienen pieni:
With one wing he swept the water,
yksi siipi vettä viisti,
To the sky was swung the other;
toinen taivasta lakaisi,
On the sea his tail he rested,
pursto merta pyyhätteli,
On the cliffs his beak he rattled.
nokka luotoja lotaisi.
Slowly back and forwards flying,
Lenteleikse, liiteleikse,
Turning all around, and gazing,
katseleikse, käänteleikse.
Soon he saw old Väinämöinen
Näki vanhan Väinämöisen
On the blue waves of the ocean.
selällä meren sinisen:
"What has brought you here, O hero,
"Mit' olet meressä, miesi,
Wandering through the waves of ocean?"
uros, aaltojen seassa?"
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"This has brought the man to ocean,
"Sit' olen meressä miesi,
Plunged the hero in the sea-waves.
uros aaltojen varassa:
I would seek the maid of Pohja,
läksin neittä Pohjolasta,
Woo the maiden of Pimentola.
impeä Pimentolasta.
"On my journey swift I hasted,
"Ajoa karautime
On the ocean's watery surface,
suloa meryttä myöten.
Till about the time of daybreak,
Niin päivänä muutamana,
Came I, after many mornings,
huomenna moniahana
Where is Luotola's deep embayment,
tulin Luotolan lahelle,
Hard by Joukola's rapid river,
Joukolan jokivesille:
When my horse was shot beneath me,
hepo alta ammuttihin,
By an arrow launched against me.
itseäni mielittihin.
"Thus I fell into the water,
"Siitä vierähin vetehen,
In the waves I plunged my fingers,
sorruin sormin lainehesen
And the wind impels me onward,
tuulen tuuiteltavaksi,
And the billows drift me forward.
aaltojen ajeltavaksi.
"Then there came a gale from north-west,
"Tulipa tuuli luotehesta,
From the east a mighty tempest,
iästä iso vihuri;
Far away the tempest drove me,
se mun kauas kannatteli,
Swimming from the land still further,
uitteli ulomma maasta.
Many days have I been floating,
Mont' olen päiveä pälynnyt,
Many days have I been swimming,
monta yötä uiksennellut
On this wide expanse of water,
näitä väljiä vesiä,
Out upon the open ocean.
ulapoita auke'ita;
And I cannot now conjecture,
enk' on tuota tunnekana,
Cannot guess, nor e'en imagine,
arvoa, älyäkänä,
How I finally shall perish,
kumpi kuoloksi tulevi,
And what death shall overtake me
kumpi ennen ennättävi:
Whether I shall die of hunger,
nälkähänkö nääntyminen,
Or shall sink beneath the waters."
vai vetehen vaipuminen."
Said the bird of air, the eagle,
Sanoi kokko, ilman lintu:
"Let thy heart be free from trouble;
"Ellös olko milläskänä!
Climb upon my back, and seat thee,
Seisotaite selkähäni,
Standing up upon my wing-tips,
nouse kynkkäluun nenille!
From the sea will I transport thee,
Mie sinun merestä kannan,
Wheresoever thou may'st fancy.
minne mielesi tekevi.
For the day I well remember,
Vielä muistan muunki päivän,
And recall a happier season,
arvoan ajan paremman,
When fell Kaleva's green forest,
kun ajoit Kalevan kasken,
Cleared was Osmola's famed island,
Osmolan salon sivallit:
But thou didst protect the birch-tree,
heitit koivun kasvamahan,
And the beauteous tree left'st standing,
puun sorean seisomahan
That the birds might rest upon it,
linnuille lepeämiksi,
And that I myself might sit there."
itselleni istumiksi."
Then the aged Väinämöinen
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Raised his head from out the water,
kohottavi kokkoansa;
From the sea the man sprang upward,
mies on nousevi merestä,
From the waves the hero mounted.
uros aallosta ajaikse,
On the eagle's wings he sat him,
siiville sijoitteleikse,
On the wing-tips of the eagle.
kokon kynkkäluun nenille.
Then the bird of air, the eagle,
Tuop' on kokko, ilman lintu,
Raised the aged Väinämöinen,
kantoi vanhan Väinämöisen,
Through the path of wind he bore him,
viepi tuulen tietä myöten,
And along the east-wind's pathway,
ahavan ratoa myöten
To the utmost bounds of Pohja,
Pohjan pitkähän perähän,
Onwards to the misty Sariola,
summahan Sariolahan.
There abandoned Väinämöinen,
Siihen heitti Väinämöisen,
Soared into the air, and left him.
itse ilmahan kohosi.
There stood Väinämöinen weeping,
Siinä itki Väinämöinen,
There stood weeping and lamenting,
siinä itki ja urisi
On the borders of the ocean,
rannalla merellisellä,
On a land whose name he knew not,
nimen tietämättömällä,
With a hundred wounds upon him,
sata haavoa sivulla,
By a thousand winds belaboured,
tuhat tuulen pieksemätä,
And his beard was much disordered,
partaki pahoin kulunut,
And his hair was all entangled.
tukka mennyt tuuhakaksi.
Thus he wept for two, and three nights,
Itki yötä kaksi, kolme,
For as many days stood weeping,
saman verran päiviäki;
For the country round he knew not,
eikä tiennyt tietä käyä,
And no path could he discover,
outo, matkoa osannut
Which perchance might lead him homeward,
palataksensa kotihin,
Back to a familiar country,
mennä maille tuttaville,
To his own, his native country,
noille syntymäsijoille,
Where he passed his days aforetime.
elomaillen entisille.
But the little maid of Pohja,
Pohjan piika pikkarainen,
Fair-haired damsel of the household,
vaimo valkeanverinen,
With the sun had made agreement,
teki liiton päivän kanssa,
And both sun and moon had promised,
päivän kanssa, kuun keralla
They would always rise together,
yhen ajan noustaksensa
And they would awake together.
ja yhen havataksensa:
She herself arose before them,
itse ennen ennätteli,
Ere the sun or moon had risen,
ennen kuuta, aurinkoa,
Long before the time of cockcrow,
kukonki kurahtamatta,
Or the chirping of a chicken.
kanan lapsen laulamatta.
From five sheep she shore the fleeces,
Viisi villoa keritsi,
Clipped the wool from off six lambkins,
kuusi lammasta savitsi,
In her loom she wove the fleeces,
villat saatteli saraksi,
And the whole with care she carded,
kaikki vatvoi vaattehiksi
Long before the dawn of morning,
ennen päivän nousemista,
Long before the sun had risen.
auringon ylenemistä.
After this she washed the tables,
Pesi siitä pitkät pöyät,
Swept the wide-extended flooring,
laajat lattiat lakaisi
With the broom of twigs all leafless,
vastasella varpaisella,
Then with broom of leafy branches.
luutasella lehtisellä.
Then the sweepings she collected
Ammueli rikkasensa
In the dustpan made of copper;
vaskisehen vakkasehen;
Out of doors she took the rubbish,
vei ne ulos usta myöten,
To the field beyond the farmyard,
pellolle pihoa myöten,
To the field's extremest limit,
perimäisen pellon päähän,
Where the lowest fence has opening.
alimaisen aian suuhun.
There she stood upon the sweepings,
Seisattelihe rikoille,
And she turned around, and listened.
kuuntelihe, kääntelihe:
From the lake she heard a weeping,
kuulevi mereltä itkun,
Sounds of woe across the river.
poikki joen juorotuksen.
Quickly then she hastened homeward,
Juosten joutuvi takaisin,
And she hurried to the parlour.
pian pirttihin menevi;
As she came, she told her tidings,
sanoi tuonne saatuansa,
In such words as those which follow:
toimitteli tultuansa:
"From the lake I hear a weeping,
"Kuulin mie mereltä itkun,
Sounds of woe across the river."
poikki joen juorotuksen."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Old and gap-toothed dame of Pohja,
Pohjan akka harvahammas,
Hastened forth into the farmyard,
pian pistihe pihalle,
Hurried to the fence's opening,
vierähti veräjän suuhun;
Where she bent her ear to listen,
siinä korvin kuunteleikse.
And she spoke the words which follow:
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"This is not like childhood's weeping
"Ei ole itku lapsen itku
Nor like women's lamentation,
eikä vaimojen valitus;
But a bearded hero weeping;
itku on partasuun urohon,
Thus weep men whose chins are bearded."
jouhileuan juorottama."
Three planks high, the boat was builded,
Työnnälti venon vesille,
Which she pushed into the water,
kolmilaian lainehille;
And herself began to row it,
itse loihe soutamahan.
And she rowed, and hastened onward
Sekä souti jotta joutui:
To the spot where Väinämöinen,
souti luoksi Väinämöisen,
Where the hero was lamenting.
luoksi itkevän urohon.
There was Väinämöinen weeping,
Siinä itki Väinämöinen,
There Uvanto's swain lamented,
urisi Uvannon sulho
By the dreary clumps of willow,
pahalla pajupurolla,
By the tangled hedge of cherry.
tiheällä tuomikolla:
Moved his mouth, his beard was shaking,
suu liikkui, järisi parta,
But his lips he did not open.
vaan ei leuka lonkaellut.
Then did Pohjola's old Mistress,
Sanoi Pohjolan emäntä,
Speak unto, and thus addressed him:
puhutteli, lausutteli:
"O thou aged man unhappy,
"Ohoh sinua, ukko utra!
Thou art in a foreign country!"
Jo olet maalla vierahalla."
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Lifted up his head and answered
päätänsä kohottelevi.
In the very words that follow:
Sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"True it is, and well I know it,
"Jo ma tuon itseki tieän:
I am in a foreign country,
olen maalla vierahalla,
Absolutely unfamiliar.
tuiki tuntemattomalla.
I was better in my country,
Maallani olin parempi,
Greater in the home I came from."
kotonani korkeampi."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"In the first place you must tell me,
"Saisiko sanoakseni,
If I may make bold to ask you,
oisiko lupa kysyä,
From what race you take your lineage,
mi sinä olet miehiäsi
And from what heroic nation?"
ja kuka urohiasi?"
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Well my name was known aforetime,
"Mainittihinpa minua,
And in former days was famous,
arveltihin aikoinansa
Ever cheerful in the evening,
illoilla iloitsijaksi,
Ever singing in the valleys,
joka laakson laulajaksi
There in Väinölä's sweet meadows,
noilla Väinölän ahoilla,
And on Kalevala's broad heathlands;
Kalevalan kankahilla.
But my grief is now so heavy
Mi jo lienenki katala,
That I know myself no longer."
tuskin tunnen itsekänä."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Rise, O man, from out the marshes,
"Nouse jo norosta, miesi,
Hero, seek another pathway.
uros, uuelle uralle,
Tell me now of thy misfortunes,
haikeasi haastamahan,
And relate me thy adventure."
satuja sanelemahan!"
Thus she made him cease his weeping,
Otti miehen itkemästä,
Made the hero cease lamenting;
urohon urisemasta;
And into her boat she took him,
saattoi siitä purtehensa,
Bade him at the stern be seated,
istutti venon perähän.
And herself resumed the oars,
Itse airoille asettui,
And she then began to row him
soutimille suorittihe;
Unto Pohjola, o'er water,
souti poikki Pohjolahan,
And she brought him to her dwelling.
viepi vierahan tupahan.
Then she fed the famished stranger,
Syötteli nälästynehen,
And she dried his dripping garments,
kastunehen kuivaeli;
Then she rubbed his limbs all stiffened,
siitä viikon hierelevi,
And she warmed him and shampooed him,
hierelevi, hautelevi:
Till she had restored his vigour,
teki miehen terveheksi,
And the hero had recovered.
urohon paranneheksi.
After this, she spoke and asked him,
Kysytteli, lausutteli,
In the very words which follow:
itse virkki, noin nimesi:
"Why did'st weep, O Väinämöinen,
"Mitä itkit, Väinämöinen,
Why lament, Uvantolainen,
uikutit, uvantolainen,
In that miserable region,
tuolla paikalla pahalla,
On the borders of the lakelet?"
rannalla meryttä vasten?"
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"Cause enough have I for weeping,
"Onpa syytä itkeäni,
Reason, too, for lamentation,
vaivoja valittoani!
In the sea I long was swimming,
Kauan oon meriä uinut,
Tossed about upon the billows,
lapioinnut lainehia
On the wide expanse of water,
noilla väljillä vesillä,
Out upon the open ocean.
ulapoilla auke'illa.
"I must weep throughout my lifespan,
"Tuota itken tuon ikäni,
And lament throughout my lifetime,
puhki polveni murehin,
That I swam beyond my country,
kun ma uin omilta mailta,
Left the country so familiar,
tulin mailta tuttavilta
And have come to doors I know not,
näille ouoille oville,
And to hedge-gates that I know not,
veräjille vierahille.
All the trees around me pain me,
Kaikki täällä puut purevi,
All the pine-twigs seem to pierce me,
kaikki havut hakkoavi,
Every birch-tree seems to flog me,
joka koivu koikkoavi,
Every alder seems to wound me,
joka leppä leikkoavi:
But the wind is friendly to me,
yks' on tuuli tuttuani,
And the sun still shines upon me,
päivä ennen nähtyäni
In this unaccustomed country,
näillä mailla vierahilla,
And within the doors I know not."
äkkiouoilla ovilla."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
siitä tuon sanoiksi saatti:
"Do not weep, O Väinämöinen,
"Elä itke, Väinämöinen,
Nor lament, Uvantolainen.
uikuta, uvantolainen!
Here 'tis good for thee to sojourn,
Hyvä tääll' on ollaksesi,
And to pass thy days in comfort.
armas aikaellaksesi,
Salmon you can eat at table,
syöä lohta luotaselta,
And beside it pork is standing."
sivulta sianlihoa."
But the aged Väinämöinen
Silloin vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
itse tuon sanoiksi virkki:
"Foreign food I do not relish,
"Kylkehen kyläinen syönti
In the best of strangers' houses.
hyvissäki vierahissa;
In his land a man is better,
mies on maallansa parempi,
In his home a man is greater.
kotonansa korkeampi.
Grant me, Jumala most gracious,
Soisipa sula Jumala,
O compassionate Creator,
antaisipa armoluoja:
Once again to reach my country,
pääsisin omille maille,
And the land I used to dwell in!
elomaillen entisille!
Better is a man's own country,
Parempi omalla maalla
Water from beneath the sabot,
vetonenki virsun alta,
Than in unfamiliar countries,
kuin on maalla vierahalla
Mead to drink from golden goblets."
kultamaljasta metonen."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"What are you prepared to give me,
"Niin mitä minullen annat,
If I send you to your country,
kun saatan omille maille,
To the borders of your cornfields,
oman peltosi perille,
Or the bath-house of your dwelling?"
kotisaunan saapuville?"
Said the aged Väinämöinen,
Sanoi vanha Väinämöinen:
"Tell me then what I shall give you,
"Mitäpä kysyt minulta,
If you send me to my country,
jos saatat omille maille,
To the borders of my cornfields,
oman peltoni perille,
There to hear my cuckoo calling,
oman käen kukkumille,
And my birds so sweetly singing.
oman linnun laulamille!
Will you choose a gold-filled helmet.
Otatko kultia kypärin,
Or a hat filled up with silver?"
hope'ita huovallisen?"
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"O thou wisest Väinämöinen,
"Ohoh viisas Väinämöinen,
Thou the oldest of the sages,
tietäjä iän-ikuinen!
Golden gifts I do not ask for,
En kysele kultiasi,
And I wish not for thy silver.
halaja hope'itasi:
Gold is but a toy for children,
kullat on lasten kukkasia,
Silver bells adorn the horses,
hopeat hevon helyjä.
But if you can forge a Sampo,
Taiatko takoa sammon,
Weld its many-coloured cover,
kirjokannen kalkutella
From the tips of swan's white wing-plumes,
joutsenen kynän nenästä,
From the milk of barren heifer,
maholehmän maitosesta,
From a single grain of barley,
yhen ohrasen jyvästä,
From a single fleece of ewe's wool,
yhen uuhen villasesta,
Then will I my daughter give you,
niin annan tytön sinulle,
Give the maiden as your guerdon,
panen neien palkastasi,
And will bring you to your country,
saatan sun omille maille,
There to hear the birds all singing,
oman linnun laulamille,
There to hear your cuckoo calling,
oman kukon kuulumille,
On the borders of your cornfields."
oman peltosi perille."
Väinämöinen, old and steadfast,
Vaka vanha Väinämöinen
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"No, I cannot forge a Sampo,
"Taia en sampoa takoa,
Nor can weld its pictured cover.
kirjokantta kirjoitella.
Only bring me to my country,
Saata mie omille maille:
And I'll send you Ilmarinen,
työnnän seppo Ilmarisen,
Who shall forge a Sampo for you,
joka samposi takovi,
Weld its many-coloured cover.
kirjokannet kalkuttavi,
He perchance may please the maiden,
neitosi lepyttelevi,
Win your daughter's young affections.
tyttäresi tyy'yttävi.
"He's a smith without an equal,
"Se on seppo sen mokoma,
None can wield the hammer like him,
ylen taitava takoja,
For 'twas he who forged the heaven,
jok' on taivoa takonut,
And who wrought the air's foundations,
ilman kantta kalkutellut:
Yet we find no trace of hammer,
ei tunnu vasaran jälki
Nor the trace of tongs discover."
eikä pihtien pitämät."
Louhi, Pohjola's old Mistress,
Louhi, Pohjolan emäntä,
Answered in the words which follow:
sanan virkkoi, noin nimesi:
"I will only yield my daughter,
"Sille työnnän tyttäreni,
And my child I promise only
sille lapseni lupoan,
To the man who welds a Sampo
joka sampuen takovi,
With its many-coloured cover,
kannen kirjo kirjoittavi
From the tips of swan's white wing-plumes,
joutsenen kynän nenästä,
From the milk of barren heifer,
maholehmän maitosesta,
From a single grain of barley,
yhen ohrasen jyvästä,
From a single fleece of ewe's wool."
yhen uuhen untuvasta."
Thereupon the colt she harnessed,
Pani varsan valjahisin,
In the front she yoked the bay one,
ruskean re'en etehen;
And she placed old Väinämöinen
saattoi vanhan Väinämöisen,
In the sledge behind the stallion.
istutti oron rekehen.
And she spoke and thus addressed him,
Siitä tuon sanoiksi virkki,
In the very words which follow:
itse lausui, noin nimesi:
"Do not raise your head up higher,
"Elä päätäsi ylennä,
Turn it not to gaze about you,
kohottele kokkoasi,
That the steed may not be wearied,
kun ei uupune oronen,
Till the evening shall have gathered.
tahi ei ilta ennättäne:
If you dare to raise your head up,
josp' on päätäsi ylennät,
Or to turn to gaze around you,
kohottelet kokkoasi,
Then misfortune will o'ertake you,
jo toki tuho tulevi,
And an evil day betide you."
paha päivä päälle saapi."
Then the aged Väinämöinen
Siitä vanha Väinämöinen
Whipped the horse, and urged him onward,
löi orosen juoksemahan,
And the white-maned courser hastened
harjan liina liikkumahan.
Noisily upon the journey,
Ajoa karittelevi
Forth from Pohjola's dark regions,
pimeästä Pohjolasta,
Sariola for ever misty.
summasta Sariolasta.